Finding Aid for Kathleen L. Vakalo Papers, 1971-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Kathleen L. Vakalo Papers 1971-1991
Vakalo, Kathleen L.
4 linear ft.
04102 Aa 2
Citizen expert on the topic of low-level radioactive waste control; accumulated materials relating to her participation and involvement in various commissions and agencies concerned with low-level radioactive waste control.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Kathleen L. Vakalo (donor no. 9499 ) and came to the library in August 2004.
The collection is open to research.
Kathleen L. Vakalo received her BA in philosophy and MA in educational psychology both from the University of Michigan. Through study and organizational participation, Vakalo became knowledgeable on the issue of low-level radioactive waste control. In 1980, Congress had passed the Low Level Waste Policy Act that shifted responsibility for the managment and disposal of low-level radioactive waste to the states. This act also encouraged states to form compacts to manage waste on a regional basis. In 1982, Michigan became the first state to pass Compact legislation in the Midwest. Subsequently six additional states signed on forming the Midwest Low-Level Radioactive Waste Compact. The purpose of the Compact (in part) was to determine which of the seven states would be chosen as host state.
In 1984, Vakalo was selected as a citizen member of the Michigan Environmental Review Board Subcommittee on Low-level Radioactive Waste. Since 1982, she had worked as a volunteer researcher on low-level radioactive waste for the Public Interest Research Group in Michigan (PIRGIM) so when the Michigan Departments of Natural Resources and Public Health needed some member of the general public to serve on the subcommittee, PIRGIM recommended Vakalo. In addition, in 1986 she was appointed by the Speaker of the Michigan House to the Michigan Radioactive Waste Control Commitee as a citizen member.
The Vakalo collection consists of accumulated materials relating to her participation and interest in groups concerned with the issue of low-level radioactive waste disposal. The collection is most valuable for files of reports, memoranda, meeting minutes, and related material. The series in the collection are: Midwest Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waster Commission; Michigan Low-Level Radioactive Waste Authority; International Low-Level Radioactive Waste Research and Education Institute; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Vakalo, Kathleen L.; International Low-Level Radioactive Waste Research and Education Institute.; Michigan Low-Level Radioactive Waste Authority.; Midwest Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Commission (U.S.); Low level radioactive waste disposal facilities--Location--Michigan.; Radioactive waste sites--Michigan.; Radioactive waste disposal--Michigan.
- Midwest Interstate Low-Level Radioactive Waste Commission
  - Annual reports, 1984-1985 1987 (Box 1)
  - Newsletter, Update, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Michigan newsletter, Update, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Regional Management Plan, 1985-1985, 12 reports (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed and reports (Box 1)
  - Chronological file
    (includes minutes, memoranda, reports, etc.)
    - 1983-1990 and undated (Box 2)
- Michigan Low-Level Radioactive Waste Authority
  - Report to the Governor, Legislature, and Department of Public Health (December 1986) (Box 3)
  - Impacts of Siting a low-level radioactive waste facilty in Michigan, June, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Meeting minutes; and proposed legislation (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous reports, meeting minutes, 3 folders (Box 3)
- International Low-Level Radioactive Waste Research and Education Institute
  - Minutes, reports, publicity, etc., 1990-1991 (Box 3)
- Topical files
  - Governor's Committee on Nuclear Waste, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Low-level radioactive waste-background information (Box 4)
  - Melson, Gail (Science Research Coordinator, Legislative Science Office
    - Memoranda, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Nuclear Waste Disposal Dateline, 1972-1980 (Box 4)
    - Thesis (M.A.), 1980 "Nuclear waste repository siting and Michigan, 1975-1977" (Box 4)
  - Michigan Nuclear Facility Emergency Plan, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Radioactive Waste Control Committee
    - General (Box 4)
    - Vakalo's appointment (Box 4)
  - Midwest Compact Committee, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Public Interest Research Group in Michigan (PIRGIM), 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Radioactive Exchange Decisionmakers forum (3rd annual) (Box 4)
  - Radioactive waste disposal (clippings), 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Saginaw County Medical Society, Committee on the Environment of the, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Sinclair (Mary) statements and memoranda (Box 4)
  - Vakalo, Kathleen
    - Resume/biography (Box 4)
    - Presentations (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)